Finding Aid for Department of Industrial and Operations Engineering (University of Michigan) records, 1957-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Industrial and Operations Engineering (University of Michigan) records 1957-2003 1985-2000
University of Michigan. Department of Industrial and Operations Engineering.
5 linear feet
9716 Bimu C146 2
Department in the College of Engineering at the University of Michigan. Publications includes brochures and pamphlets, graduate study bulletins, directories, manuals, departmental review reports, and yearbooks. Also includes publications from the Center for Occupational Health and Safety Engineering, and the Engineering Human Performance and Safety Laboratory. Also includes the publication IOE Alumni Newsletter, as well as the student publications The Rag and Industrial Blueprint.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records are received periodically from the unit (donor no. 8498 ). Latest accessions were received in 1996 and 2003.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The records are open for research.
Operations Engineering is concerned with the integration of humans and machines to optimize the performance of manufacturing and operation of systems. The field more specifically looks at the way these systems are analyzed and designed. The Department of Industrial and Operations Engineering (IOE) was started at the University of Michigan in 1956 because of the increasing importance of mathematical modeling and computers in manufacturing. The department began by offering curriculum focused on human performance, the economics of engineering, facility planning, and quality control. The department has become even more involved due to its increasing use of computers and mathematical modeling. As of 2013, the department moved its operations and is currently located on North Campus. The Department of Industrial and Operations Engineering at the University of Michigan is internationally regarded and one of the United States' top programs in the field.
The Department of Industrial and Operations Engineering Records are divided into two series: Publications and Departmental Records.
Departmental records include chronological files, committee meeting minutes, and presentation agendas. The bulk of the publications document the Department of Industrial and Operations Engineering. The Publications series is composed of Unit Publication, Sub-Unit Publications, and Student Publications. The Unit Publications subseries contains printed material published specifically by the Department of Industrial and Operations Engineering. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Industrial and Operations Engineering.; University of Michigan. Center for Occupational Health and Safety Engineering.; University of Michigan. Engineering Human Performance and Safety Laboratory.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Center for Occupational Health and Safety Engineering.; University of Michigan. Engineering Human Performance and Safety Laboratory.
Genre Terms:
Pamphlets.; Bulletins.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Reports.; School yearbooks.; Directories.; Student publications.
- Publications
  - Unit Publications
    The Publications series (1 linear foot) is divided into three subseries: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications, and Student Publications. The Unit Publications subseries includes brochures, bulletins, flyers, manuals, newsletters, reports, schedules, and yearbooks. The bulletins describe the graduate program of Industrial and Operations Engineering from 1969 to 1995. In 1975 the department asked its graduates to fill out a single sheet of information. This directory, entitled Alumni Biographical Data, includes the graduate's name, address, year of graduation, spouse's name, names of children, present position held and contact information, and a brief biography of activities since graduation. Some alumni expanded the questionnaire to include bibliographies and other information. Under manuals the researcher will find handbooks for both graduate and undergraduate students. The Undergraduate Student Guide documents the undergraduate program from 1980 to 1998. The only newsletter found in this subseries is the IOE Alumni Newsletter. The Bentley Library's holdings include these newsletters from 1986,1989 and from 1990 to 1999. There are departmental review reports from 1977, 1981, and 1986. The researcher will find time schedules for courses taught in IOE from 1986 to 1998. An almost continuous run of undergraduate yearbooks from 1991 to 2000, with the exception of 1993, document student life in the department. These yearbooks include individual photograph of IOE students and candid shots of their social and career-oriented activities.
    - Brochures
      - Industrial and Operations Engineering, 1972-1993 (Box 1)
      - Industrial Engineering, 1957-1969 (Box 1)
    - Bulletins
      - Graduate Programs in Industrial Engineering, 1969, undated (Box 1)
      - Graduate Programs in Industrial and Operations Engineering, 1973-1977 (Box 1)
      - Graduate Study and Research, [1995] (Box 1)
      - Graduate Study and Research in Industrial and Operations Engineering, undated (Box 1)
    - Directories
      - Alumni Biographical Data, 1975 (Box 1)
      - Faculty Activities 1987 (Box 1)
    - Flyers
      - Graduate Programs in Industrial and Operations Engineering, 1978-1979, undated (Box 1)
    - Manuals
      - Handbook for Graduate Students, 1977 (Box 1)
      - Undergraduate Student Guide, 1980-1987, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
      - Undergraduate Guide for Industrial and Operations Engineers, 1991-1993 (Box 1)
      - Undergraduate Study Guide, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Newsletters
      - IOE Alumni Newsletter
        - 1986 (Box 1)
        - 1989 (Box 1)
        - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
        - 1992-1993 (Box 1)
        - 1994-1995 (Box 1)
        - 1996 (Box 1)
        - 1997 (Box 1)
        - 1999 (Box 1)
    - Reports
      - Departmental Reviews
        - 1977 (Box 1)
        - 1981 (Box 1)
        - 1986 (Box 1)
      - Network Models for Large-Scale Time-Sharing Systems, 1971 (Box 1)
      - Research Activities in Industrial and Operations Engineering, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Schedules
      - Time Schedules, 1986-1998, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Yearbooks
      - Industrial Operations Engineering Yearbook, 1994-2000, 6 folders (Box 1)
      - IOE Undergraduate Yearbook
        - 1991-1992 (Box 1)
        - 1994 (Box 1)
  - Sub-Unit Publications
    The Sub-Unit Publications subseries contains publications from subordinate offices, departments, programs and organizations within the Department of Industrial and Operations Engineering. These publications are arranged alphabetically by the creating sub-unit. The Sub-Unit Publications subseries includes brochures and bulletins from the Academic Peer Counseling Office, the Center for Occupational Health and Safety Engineering, the Continuing Education Program, the Engineering Human Performance and Safety Laboratory, the Program in Manufacturing Systems Engineering.
    - Academic Peer Counseling Office 1997 (Box 1)
    - Center for Occupational Health and Safety Engineering 1978-1979, 1996, undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Continuing Education Programs 1985 (Box 1)
    - Engineering Human Performance and Safety Laboratory 1974 (Box 1)
    - Program in Manufacturing Systems Engineering 1978-1979, undated (Box 1)
  - Student Publications
    The Student Publications subseries contains publications published by student groups within the Department of Industrial and Operations Engineering. This subseries includes two publications. The Bentley Historical Library holds volumes 1 and 4 of The Rag published in 1988 and 1990/1991. The name changed in 1991 and became the Industrial Blueprint. This student newsletter continued at least until 2000 with volume 14.
    - Newsletters
      - The Rag, 1988, 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Industrial Blueprint vol. 5-14, 1991-2003, 12 folders (Box 1)
        (replaces The Rag)
    - Alpha Pi Mu
      - Directories
        - undated (Box 1)
- Departmental Records
  The Departmental Records series contains 4 linear feet of files. The chronological files are the correspondence and other handouts from the various administrators and faculty members in the department. These typically cover the projects of the department as well as some of problems faced by the staff. The collection also contains minutes for some of the committees such as the graduate, Ph.D., Steering Review, and others. These records document the problems, solutions, and discussion of the department as a whole, as well as student finances and Ph.D. candidates. The large majority of the collection is made up of binders of the agendas of various presentations. These presentations covered business interactions with companies in Japan, China, and Asia as a whole. These topics were presented by the IOE, with the help of some of the other departments on campus.
  - Chronological Files, 1978-1993, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Committees
    - Graduate Committee
      - 1974-1976, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1974-1976, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - Financial Aid Committee, 1974-1976, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Admissions, Financial Aid, and Graduate Programs, 1976-1979, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Ph.D. Committee, 1972, 1974, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Rules of the Faculty of the College of Engineering (Box 2)
    - Steering Review, 1968-1981, 26 folders (Box 2)
  - Presentation Agendas
    - Presentations on conducting business with Japanese companies, 1985, 1990-1992 (4 binders) (Box 3)
    - Presentations on conducting business with Japanese companies, 1988 (Box 4)
    - Presentations on conducting business with Asian companies, 1988-1992 (3 binders) (Box 4)
    - Presentations on conducting business with Chinese companies, 1990-1991 (3 binders) (Box 5)